{"tossups": [{"question": "In 1863, this person and James Montgomery led a successful raid on the Combahee River. This abolitionist was nicknamed by William Lloyd Garrison due to a similarity with a prophet in the Book of Exodus. This woman helped circumvent the Fugitive Slave Act by leading expeditions down the Chesapeake coast of Maryland. For ten points, name this former slave, known as \u201cMoses,\u201d who guided many escaped slaves to the North on the Underground Railroad.", "answer": "Harriet<b> Tubman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In a myth about this location, the Devil threw a rock at a friar, creating the \u201cFriar\u2019s Heel\u201d about 100 feet from a \u201cSlaughter Stone.\u201d William Stukeley hypothesized that this site was used as a Druid place of worship. The sunset of the winter solstice aligns with this site, which is located on the Salisbury plain. For ten points, name this prehistoric monument of England, a ring of standing stones.", "answer": "<b> Stonehenge</b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "A type of music native to this country features the five-string vihuela and the deep-bodied, low-pitched guitarron. A folk song with an uneven five-four rhythm about a legless arthropod became popular during this country\u2019s revolution, with lyrics making fun of Victoriano Huerta sung by partisans of Pancho Villa. For ten points, name this country where songs like \u201cLa Cucaracha\u201d and \u201cLa Bamba\u201d are played by mariachi bands south of the United States.", "answer": "<b> Mexico</b> (or the<b> United Mexican States</b> or<b> Estados Unidos Mexicanos</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "During this event, John Indian was ordered to prepare a cake made of urine to feed to a dog. Cotton Mather addressed a letter to the instigators of this event warning them against using \u201cspectral evidence.\u201dOne part of this event focused on the slave Tituba\u2019s alleged spiritual influence over young children. Twenty people died during the hysteria of, for ten points, what late 17th century tragedy in Massachusetts over supposed evil magic?", "answer": "<b> Salem witch trials</b> (accept descriptive answers that mention all three aspects of the answer; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Valentina Tereshkova and Yuri Gagarin were members of, for ten points, what Cold War-era program that, in 1957, launched<em> Sputnik</em> into orbit?", "answer": "<b> Soviet</b> Union\u2019s<b> space</b> program (or<b> Kosmicheskaya programma SSSR</b>; accept<b> Russia</b>n <b>space</b> program; accept descriptive answers; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This ruler overthrew the Chagatai Khanate after his capture of Balkh and defeated the leader of the Golden Horde, Tokhtamysh, at the Kur River. This man defeated the Tughluq Dynasty by setting camels on fire to scare elephants. This ruler brought back the spoils from his sacks of Damascus and Delhi to his capital of Samarkand. For ten points, name this Turkic conqueror of Central Asia who suffered from a limp.", "answer": "<b> Timur</b> the Lame (or<b> Tamerlane</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This politician used the slogan \u201cin your guts you know he\u2019s nuts\u201d to mock his opponent\u2019s campaign slogan; he also attacked that opponent with an advertisement featuring a girl picking at a daisy before a nuclear explosion. This President signed amendments to Social Security that created Medicare and Medicaid, and he declared \u201cWar on Poverty\u201d as part of his Great Society program. For ten points, name this Texan US president who succeeded John F. Kennedy.", "answer": "<b> L</b>yndon Baines<b> Johnson</b> (accept<b> LBJ</b>; prompt on Johnson)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician attempted to stall the construction of the Hinckley nuclear power station out of fears of Chinese involvement. This figure was criticized after reportedly covering up the misfire of a Trident missile in June 2016. She appointed the highly controversial Boris Johnson as Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and in March 2017 she invoked Article 50 to formally begin the Brexit process. For ten points, name this successor of David Cameron as prime minister of the United Kingdom.", "answer": "Theresa<b> May</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "A building featuring a coffered one of these structures was originally commissioned by Marcus Agrippa and renovated by Hadrian. Constantino Brumidi decorated the interior surface of one of these structures with murals that can be seen from the rotunda below. An oculus allows light to shine into the Pantheon through, for ten points, what architectural feature that serves as the roof of the United States Capitol building?", "answer": "<b> dome</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "A treaty negotiated by this man and Colonel Edward House was targeted for change by the Lodge Reservations. Before becoming the Governor of New Jersey, this politician served as Princeton University\u2019s president. This President asked Congress for a declaration of war after news of the Zimmermann Telegram broke. For ten points, name this US President who failed in his promise to \u201ckeep us out of\u201d World War I.", "answer": "Thomas Woodrow<b> Wilson</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s reign, his brother\u2019s general Kitbuqa lost the Battle of Ain Jalut, the first time his empire\u2019s army had been halted entirely. This man defeated Ariq Boke in the Toluid civil war before being named Khan. This man\u2019s invasions of Japan were twice halted by the<em> kamikaze</em> winds. For ten points, name this founder of the Yuan Dynasty, a Mongol leader who was the grandson of Genghis Khan.", "answer": "<b> Kublai</b> Khan", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This scientist described the \u201cchemistry of the imponderable\u201d in a Nobel Prize lecture explaining the work of Henri Becquerel. This scientist co-authored a study comparing tumor cell and healthy cell death rates when exposed to an element that this chemist isolated in 1910, four years after the death of her husband Pierre. The first woman to win a Nobel Prize was, for ten points, what Polish-French physicist who discovered radium while studying radioactive decay?", "answer": "Marie<b> Sklodowska Curie</b> (accept either or both names)", "metadata": "Science - Chemistry"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "Bradford Washburn, the first person to climb the West Buttress route on this mountain, was married to Barbara Polk, the first woman to climb this mountain. Walter Harper, a member of the Koyukon tribe, was the first to climb this mountain in 1913. President Obama\u2019s 2015 executive order renaming this mountain was supported by Lisa Murkowski and denounced by Ohio politicians. For ten points, name this highest mountain in North America, formerly named for a U.S. President.", "answer": "<b> Denali</b> (accept Mount<b> McKinley</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>A prominent port on this body of water was once ruled by a</b><em><b> zamorin</b></em><b> and was the most dominant city on the Malabar Coast. During the Ming Dynasty, Zheng He asserted Chinese</b> <b>dominance over (+)</b> <b>trade routes in and around this ocean. To reach Calicut, Vasco da</b> <b>trade routes in and around this ocean. To reach Calicut, Vasco da</b> <b>Gama rounded the Cape of (*)</b> <b>Gama rounded the Cape of (*)</b> Good Hope and sailed along and across this body of water. The endpoint of the Brahmaputra and Ganges rivers is, for ten points, what South Asian ocean between Africa and Australia?", "answer": "<b> Indian</b> Ocean (accept<b> Arabian</b> Sea until \u201cocean\u201d is read; after, anti-prompt by saying \u201cI need you to be less specific\u201d)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>This general dislodged his opponents from Gaines\u2019s Mill after the wounding of Joseph Johnston at Seven Pines allowed him to take command; that victory was part of this</b> <b>general\u2019s Seven Days Battles against George (+)</b> <b>McClellan. Because this man\u2019s family</b> <b>home stood across the Potomac River overlooking the capital, the government seized it and built (*)</b> Arlington National Cemetery on its grounds. For ten points, name this man who commanded the Army of Northern Virginia and surrendered at Appomattox Court House, ending the Civil War.", "answer": "Robert E(dward)<b> Lee</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>Early in this monarch\u2019s reign, the Earl of Bute was employed as prime minister. Newgate Prison burned down during the reign of this monarch, who also faced the Gordon Riots. George Grenville worked under this monarch, who barred expansion west of the (+)</b> <b>Appalachians. Lord North passed the Townshend Acts and the (*)</b> Intolerable Acts while serving, for ten points, what English king who rejected the Olive Branch Petition.and lost control over the colonies in the American Revolution?", "answer": "<b> George III</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This man faced off against Royalists under Miguel de la Torre in a crucial 1821 battle. This man, who assumed control of the armies of the United Provinces after issuing the</b> <b>Cartagena Manifesto, sanctioned indiscriminate killing by his forces in the (+)</b> <b>Decree of</b> <b>War to the Death. After winning the Battle of Carabobo, this leader presided over the founding of Gran (*) </b> Colombia. For ten points, name this Venezuelan independence fighter who liberated large areas of South America and is the namesake of a South American country.", "answer": "Simon (Jose Antonio de la Santisima Trinidad de)<b> Bolivar</b> (y Palacios)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>This government\u2019s attempt to unify Protestantism was opposed by Dietrich Bonhoeffer\u2019s Confessing Church. The Red Orchestra and White Rose groups opposed this government, which attacked modernist art at the (+) Degenerate Art Exhibition. Leni Riefenstahl\u2019s film </b><em><b>Triumph of the Will</b></em><b> was produced with the help of Joseph (*) </b> Goebbels, this government\u2019s propaganda minister. For ten points, name this regime that created the Nuremberg Laws to persecute Jews before engineering the Holocaust.", "answer": "<b> Nazi</b> Germany (accept<b> Germany</b>; accept<b> N</b>ational<b> S</b>ocialist<b> G</b>erman<b> W</b>orkers\u2019<b> P</b>arty; accept the<b> Third Reich</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>During this time period, a hunger march called the Jarrow Crusade marched to London, where the House of Commons completely ignored them. In this time period, Francis</b> <b>Townsend proposed a two-percent transaction tax to fund an (+)</b> <b>Old Age Revolving</b> <b>Pension Plan. The Smoot Hawley Act may have worsened the effects of this time period, in which vagrants were arrested for (*)</b> \u201criding the rails\u201d and living in Hoovervilles. For ten points, name this period of history that followed the 1929 Wall Street Crash and adversely affected economies around the world.", "answer": "<b> Great Depression</b> <b>Extra Question</b> Only read if you need a backup or tiebreaker!", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>John Glover defended this city from attack at Pell\u2019s Point after the enemy landed</b> <b>at Throg\u2019s Neck. In this city, loyalists helped William Howe\u2019s men bypass Jamaica</b> <b>Pass. Continental Army officers gave farewells in this city\u2019s (+)</b> <b>Fraunces Tavern</b> <b>after a British occupation that lasted until 1783. Fort Washington stands in this</b> <b>modern-day city, which is connected to Fort (*) </b> Lee in the New Jersey Palisades by the George Washington Bridge. The Battle of Long Island occurred in, for ten points, what city that is composed of five boroughs?", "answer": "<b> New York</b> City (or<b> NYC</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}